<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>post-cranium | Thomas A. Püschel</title>
    <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/tag/post-cranium/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.thomaspuschel.com/tag/post-cranium/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>post-cranium</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/images/icon_hu1f603fc43e6c77e42e3bc72fd8fb4d4a_30883_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>post-cranium</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/tag/post-cranium/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primate evolutionary morphology Assessing ecomorphological questions in extant and extinct anthropoids</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/oxpaleoclub/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/oxpaleoclub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paleontología virtual un conjunto de herramientas emergente para análisis morfo-funcionales en contextos evolutivos</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/socchianat/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/socchianat/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing the body morphology of the first metacarpal in the Homininae using 3D geometric morphometrics</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/morley/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/morley/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>African Miocene mammals</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/project/african-miocene-mammals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/project/african-miocene-mammals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;african-miocene-mammals&#34;&gt;African Miocene mammals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of our understanding of vertebrate evolution and human origins in the late Cenozoic of Africa derives from Miocene and Pliocene fossil localities distributed along the East African Rift System (EARS). In particular, the Miocene is a fascinating time period that compared with the epochs that followed, it is outstandingly long. It lasted from about 23 million to 5 million years ago, which logically means that the world changed far more over this time period than it did during the following epochs. Interestingly, most of the mammal species that were alive during the Miocene are at least roughly classifiable to modern mammalian groups. However, it is also important to keep in mind that it was also an of epoch characterised by change, with many older forms of mammal still surviving, only to die out before the Miocene’s end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climatic and environmental factors are strong drivers of evolution, and it is expected that these processes played a central role in these evolutionary changes observed during this epoch. Consequently, several hypotheses have been advanced to relate climate and environmental fluctuations with important events in the evolution of different mammalian lineages. However, many of these hypotheses are limited by the biogeographic gap dividing South and East African paleontological sites located in the EARS. Even though this area has crucially contributed to our understanding of vertebrate and human evolution in the late Cenozoic of Africa, the distribution of fossil sites along the rift is extremely biased towards its northern areas, and the types of palaeoenvironments are predominantly circumscribed to fluvial and lacustrine locations. Fortunately, the situation is now changing as a consequence of the finding of several fossiliferous sites located within Gorongosa National Park, Mozambique at the southernmost point of the EARS. Fossils from these sites comprise dicot trees, palms, invertebrates, reptiles, fishes, invertebrates, and mammals. Mammals are more abundant than other vertebrates, even though most specimens are fragmentary postcranial elements, as well as dental elements. This emerging fossil record, as well as the sedimentological reconstruction of this location, suggest a palaeoenvironmental mosaic of estuarine-riverine forest/woodland systems, thus representing the first coastal Miocene habitat identified in the EARS. This unique setting can allow us to assess currently untested hypotheses such as those that predict that hominoids originated in coastal forest settings, as well as those proposing that deltaic components were fundamental during human evolution. The emerging mammalian record from these areas can certainly provide fundamental information about the interaction of environmental change and mammalian evolution, including processes that likely affected hominin evolution. Fossil mammals represent a unique source of information about the Earth’s past, since individual species and entire assemblages can expose the distinctive characteristics of the mammalian community in a given place and time, thus playing a fundamental role in our understanding of how lifeforms evolved in different settings over geological time.  During the 2019 field season in Gorongosa, more than 400 fossils were found. Therefore, I am currently describing and identifying these new fossil findings, as well as comparing them with Miocene fossil materials from other African regions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primate morphology</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/project/primate_morphology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/project/primate_morphology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;primate-evolutionary-morphology&#34;&gt;Primate evolutionary morphology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important part of my research has been devoted to the study of the key adaptations defining different stages of anthropoid evolution. I am interested in the selective pressures responsible for specific evolutionary transitions, in particular (but not limited to) the split between the lineages leading to humans and apes, and the adaptive radiation of New World monkeys. For some of this work I was awarded two scholarships by the Chilean National Research and Development Agency, as well as a European Synthesis Grant. This work can be further divided into the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;•	&lt;strong&gt;Adaptive radiation of New World monkeys&lt;/strong&gt;: Platyrrhines are a diverse group of primates that presently occupy a broad range of tropical-equatorial environments in the Americas. I am particularly interested in the phenotypic adaptations, the main drivers of diversification, the role and importance of abiotic and biotic factors, and the processes that underlie the adaptive radiation of this highly diverse group, since their origin ~35-45 million years ago. I use 3D morphometrics and phylogenetic comparative analyses to identify major shifts in phenotypic evolution (in different anatomical structures) through time and to determine whether phenotypic shifts are synchronous with key geological, climatic or other environmental changes.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-traitgram-of-a-talar-centroid-size-and-b-body-mass-of-the-40-extant-platyrrhine-species-httpsdoiorg101016jjhevol201707015&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/Fig7.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Traitgram of a) talar centroid size and b) body mass of the 40 extant platyrrhine species https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2017.07.015&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/Fig7.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Traitgram of a) talar centroid size and b) body mass of the 40 extant platyrrhine species &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2017.07.015&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhevol.2017.07.015&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	&lt;strong&gt;Primate post-cranial adaptive evolution&lt;/strong&gt;: As a result of the varying demands and constraints of the diverse ecological niches where primates live, their behaviours are congruently complex, plastic and diverse, which means that the relationship between a particular morphology and certain behaviour are not straightforward. Consequently, I want to understand the evolution of primate locomotor behaviours and their anatomical correlates, and how we can apply this knowledge to the fossil record. My research is hypothesis-driven and relies on an interdisciplinary approach that integrates experimental methods with traditional and state-of-the-art morphometrics, computational biomechanics, and may use data acquired from live animals, cadaveric materials, extant and fossil skeletons, and 3D imaging (e.g. CT data).&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-platyrrhine-phylomorphospace-the-first-two-morphometric-pcs-and-stress-values-mwm-as-vertical-z-axis-one-of-the-models-closest-to-the-mean-shape-was-warped-to-match-the-multivariate-mean-using-the-thin-plate-spline-method-and-then-the-obtained-average-model-was-warped-to-represent-the-variation-along-the-pc-axes-in-addition-the-von-mises-stress-maps-of-two-extreme-models-are-displayed-to-facilitate-the-understanding-of-the-z-axis-httpdxdoiorg101098rsif20180520&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/bio-mech.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Platyrrhine phylomorphospace: the first two morphometric PCs and stress values (MWM) as vertical z-axis. One of the models closest to the mean shape was warped to match the multivariate mean using the thin-plate spline method, and then the obtained average model was warped to represent the variation along the PC axes. In addition, the von Mises stress maps of two extreme models are displayed to facilitate the understanding of the z-axis http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2018.0520&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/bio-mech.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Platyrrhine phylomorphospace: the first two morphometric PCs and stress values (MWM) as vertical z-axis. One of the models closest to the mean shape was warped to match the multivariate mean using the thin-plate spline method, and then the obtained average model was warped to represent the variation along the PC axes. In addition, the von Mises stress maps of two extreme models are displayed to facilitate the understanding of the z-axis &lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2018.0520&#34;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rsif.2018.0520&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	&lt;strong&gt;The evolution of the ape and human hands&lt;/strong&gt;: Inferring the locomotor behaviour of the last common ancestor (LCA) of African apes and humans is still a divisive subject. An African great-ape-like ancestor using knuckle-walking is the most parsimonious hypothesis for the LCA, despite diverse conflicting lines of evidence. Using morphometrics, computational biomechanics, and phylogenetic comparative methods, my colleagues and I have been working in modelling the evolution of human and ape hand morphology. This is fundamental to understand the origins of the modern human hand and its precision grip capabilities, tool use, and the locomotor repertoire of the LCA.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-biomechanical-hand-posture-models-describing-the-variation-found-between-pan-and-gorilla-httpsdoiorg101038s41598-020-60590-6&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/knuckle.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Biomechanical hand posture models describing the variation found between Pan and Gorilla https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-60590-6&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/knuckle.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Biomechanical hand posture models describing the variation found between Pan and Gorilla &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-60590-6&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-60590-6&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	&lt;strong&gt;Mandibular ecomorphology&lt;/strong&gt;: Diet is regarded as one of the main factors underlying the behavioural and ecological differences among living primates, and consequently primate diets have been more exhaustively documented than any other aspect of their behaviour. A substantial proportion of physiological and anatomical adaptations have as their fundamental objective the transformation of the food that animals consume. Many studies have focused on the mandibular adaptations because the lower jaw is mostly involved in food consumption, and hence it would be expected that its morphology better reflects diet adaptations.This relationship between primate mandibular form and diet has been previously analysed by applying a wide array of techniques and approaches. Nonetheless, most of these studies compared few species and/or infrequently aimed to elucidate function based on an explicit biomechanical framework. Therefore, my colleagues and I have been working to better understand this relationship using computational biomechanics and morphometrics. This is relevant not only to understand ecomorphological adaptations in extant species but also to carry out dietary reconstructions in fossil taxa.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-values-of-the-percentile-m50-of-the-von-mises-stress-for-both-extinct-and-extant-primate-species-a-composite-phylogeny-includind-molecular-data-from-extant-primates-and-morphological-information-from-fossils-has-been-plotted-next-to-the-von-mises-stress-distribution-of-all-the-analysed-specimens-under-the-four-different-bite-cases-httpsdoiorg101038s41598-020-63739-5&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/broad.jpg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Values of the percentile M50 of the von Mises stress for both extinct and extant primate species. A composite phylogeny includind molecular data from extant primates and morphological information from fossils has been plotted next to the von Mises stress distribution of all the analysed specimens under the four different bite cases https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-63739-5&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/img/broad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Values of the percentile M50 of the von Mises stress for both extinct and extant primate species. A composite phylogeny includind molecular data from extant primates and morphological information from fossils has been plotted next to the von Mises stress distribution of all the analysed specimens under the four different bite cases &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-63739-5&#34;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-63739-5&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Its Feet on the Ground Elucidating *Paralouatta*’s Semi-Terrestriality Using the Virtual Morpho-Functional Toolbox</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/getting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/getting/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The biomechanical importance of the scaphoid-centrale fusion during simulated knuckle-walking and its implications for human locomotor evolution</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/scaphoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/scaphoid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual ecomorphology</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/ibero2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/ibero2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Elucidating Paralouatta’s semi-terrestriality using the virtual morpho-functional toolbox</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/aapa2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/talk/aapa2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Find the paper 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/getting/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inferring locomotor behaviours in Miocene New World monkeys using finite element analysis, geometric morphometrics and machine-learning classification techniques applied to talar morphology</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/interface/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/interface/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morpho-functional analyses of the primate skeleton applying 3D geometric morphometrics, finite element analysis and phylogenetic comparative methods to assess ecomorphological questions in extant and extinct anthropoids</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/phd/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The evolution of the platyrrhine talus A comparative analysis of the phenetic affinities of the Miocene platyrrhines with their modern relatives</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/jhe/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/jhe/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taxonomic comments of a *Glossotherium* specimen from the Pleistocene of Central Chile</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/hans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/hans/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Standing on the Shoulders of Apes Analyzing the Form and Function of the Hominoid Scapula Using Geometric Morphometrics and Finite Element Analysis</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/ajpa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/ajpa/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Femoral Functional Adaptation A Comparison Between Hunter Gatherers and Farmers Using Geometric Morphometrics</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/femur/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/femur/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biomechanical modelling of Human Femora a comparison between Agriculturalists and Hunter-Gatherers using FEA, GMM and Beam Theory</title>
      <link>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/msc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.thomaspuschel.com/publication/msc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
